A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 2001-2010 (bulk 2005-2009)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Office of the Secretary of Education, 2001-2010 (bulk 2005-2009)
The Library of Virginia
44681
31.69 cu. ft. (53 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. If redaction was not an option, the entire document was sealed, but not removed from the collection. Sealed information may include, but is not limited to: medical information, social security numbers, and official student records.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Secretary of Education, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. Accession 44681 transferred and accessioned on 12 January 2010.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
The Secretary of Education assists the Governor in the development and implementation of the state's education policy. The secretary provides guidance to 16 colleges and universities, the Virginia Community College System, five higher education and research centers, the Department of Education, the state-supported museums, and other agencies in the Education Secretariat. All secretaries are appointed by the governor and serve at his will.
During the Administration of Governor Timothy M. Kaine (2006-2010) the Secretary of Education directed policy for education programs that involve multiple agencies including: Department of Education, Library of Virginia, Frontier Culture Museum of Virginia, Gunston Hall, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Science Museum of Virginia and Virginia Commission for the Arts. While Virginia's Colleges and Universities are semi-autonomous, the Secretary of Education also plays a role in directing state policy for: Virginia Community Colleges, Christopher Newport University, George Mason University, James Madison University, Longwood University, Mary Washington University, Norfolk State University, Old Dominion University, Radford University, Richard Bland College, University of Virginia, Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia State University, Virginia Tech, College of William and Mary, Roanoke Higher Education Center, Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center, and State Council of Higher Education.
Some of Governor Kaine's education initiatives were: early childhood initiatives, high school reform initiatives, Achieve: American Diploma Project, and teacher quality.
On 6 January 2006, Governor-elect Tim Kaine named Dr. Thomas Morris as Secretary of Education. Prior to his appointment, Dr. Morris served as the president of Emory and Henry College for 13 1/2 years. A distinguished Constitutional scholar and political scientist, he was a distinguished faculty member at the University of Richmond for 21 years.
A native of Galax, Virginia, Secretary Morris earned a bachelor's degree in government at Virginia Military Institute, studied at Princeton University, then completed master's and doctoral degrees in government at the University of Virginia. He received fellowships for additional advanced study including a year as a Liberal Arts Fellow at the Harvard Law School and a year as a fellow of the National Endowment for the Humanities at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
During his teaching career at the University of Richmond, Dr. Morris was selected to leadership posts and honored for excellence in the classroom. He was honored as a University Distinguished Educator, received many faculty research grants, and served as chair of the Faculty Council.
Secretary Morris is widely known as an expert on Virginia government and politics. He is the author or co-author of four books, including Virginia Government and Politics: Readings and Comments, Fourth Revised Edition, a 1998 work co-edited with Larry Sabato of the University of Virginia. He co-authored a chapter entitled "Republicans Surge in the Competitive Dominion" in a book published by LSU Press, Southern Politics in the 1990s. He also wrote a chapter on Virginia Governor Douglas Wilder for a nationally circulated book entitled Governors and Hard Times, published in 1992 by Congressional Quarterly Press, and in 1994 a chapter on Virginia and the Voting Rights Act in Quiet Revolution in the South, Princeton University Press. Dr. Morris has written an additional 17 major articles or book chapters.
Dr. Morris was well known as a political analyst for television, radio, and print media over a period of twenty-five years. He chaired the Commission on Virginia's State and Local Tax Structure for the 21st Century (1999-2000) and was a member of Governor Warner's Commission on Efficiency and Effectiveness (2002). [biography from the Virginia Secretary of Education archived website]
Scope and Content
The Records of the Virginia Secretary of Education are housed in fifty three (53 boxes). The collection is arranged into eight (8) series. Series have been designated for: I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 2002-2010; II. Constituent Correspondence, 2006-2010; III. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009); IV. Weekly Report Files, 2006-2009; V. Decision Briefs: Supporting Documentation, 2008-2010; VI. Public Relations, 2006-2009; VII. Legislative Files, 2007; and VIII. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2002-2010. These records include agendas, articles, briefings, correspondence, e-mails, grants, handouts, legislation, lists, memorandums, minutes, notes, presentations, press releases, reports, speeches, studies, surveys and files by subject. These records document the work of the Secretary of Education under Governor Tim Kaine. The most significant and voluminous material documents the development and implementation of the various educational initiatives of the Kaine Administration including: P-16 Council, Start Strong Council, Smart Beginnings, High School Reform (NGA Honors States Grant and Commonwealth Scholars), and Teacher Quality.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 2002-2010
II. Constituent Correspondence, 2006-2010
III. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009):
Subseries A. Correspondence of Secretary Thomas R. Morris, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)
Subseries B. Files of Judy Heiman, Deputy Secretary of Education, 2003-2007
Subseries C. Files of Dietra Trent, Deputy Secretary of Education, 2005-2009
Subseries D. Files of Jean Bankos, Senior Advisor to the Governor for Educational Projects, 2001-2009
Subseries E. Files of Kendall Tyree, Special Assistant to the Secretary, 2002, 2005-2007
IV. Weekly Report Files, 2006-2009
V. Decision Briefs: Supporting Documentation, 2008-2010
VI. Public Relations, 2006-2009
VII. Legislative Files, 2007
VIII. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2002-2010:
Subseries A. Virginia's P-16 Education Council, 2006-2009
Subseries B. Early Childhood Initiatives, 2002-2009
Subseries C. High School Reform Initiatives, 2002-2007
Subseries D. Achieve: American Diploma Project (ADP), 2006-2008
Subseries E. Workforce Development, 2006-2010
Subseries F. Teacher Quality, 2006
Related Material
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR-TIM KAINE
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). The Secretary of Education Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine administration. This series contains 27002 emails in ten (10) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Thomas Morris Email; B. Judith Heiman Email; C. Dietra Trent Email; D. Douglas Garcia Email; E. Jean Bankos Email; F. Kathy Glazer Email; G. Kendall Tyree Email; H. June Hines Email; I. Lorraine Lintecum Email; and J. Nicholas Galvin Email. There are 14 protected and confidential emails that are restricted from public access per Code of Virginia, 42-1-78. The Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal provides access to the Kaine email collection and includes guides to other Kaine administration records.
The Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Anne Holton), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Bob McDonnell and William C. Mims), two statewide officials elected in the same cycle as Governor Kaine.
The Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports Digital Collection contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Governor's Cabinet, including the Secretaries of Administration (Viola Baskerville), Agriculture and Forestry (Robert S. Bloxom), Commerce and Trade (Patrick O. Gottschalk), Commonwealth (Daniel C. LeBlanc, Jan-Mar. 2006 and Katherine K. Hanley (Mar. 2006-2010), Education (Dr. Thomas R. Morris), Finance (Jody Wagner, 2006-2008 and Richard D. Brown, 2008-2010), Health and Human Resources (Marilyn Tavenner), Natural Resources (Preston Bryant), Public Safety (John W. Marshall), Technology (Aneesh Chopra, 2006-2009 and Leonard M. Pomata, 2009-2010), and Transportation (Pierce Homer). Also included are reports by the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness (Robert Crouch), Office of Constituent Services (Marc Cheatham, 2006-2007 and Amber Amato, 2007-2010), Press Office, Policy Office and Virginia Liaison Office. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor that he took with him at the end of the day on Friday. A second copy of the report was made for the Chief of Staff. The level of detail varied for each cabinet officer and items of importance were highlighted by staff for the Governor. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. Governor Kaine wrote handwritten notes and/or marked-up some reports with post-it notes and requested follow up information from the person submitting the report. Those questions and answers are included in this series. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Kaine Administration.
The Executive Orders Digital Collection includes 110 executive orders and 9 executive directives issued by Governor Kaine.
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). The Policy Office Records of Governor Timothy M. Kaine are housed in 174 boxes. The collection is arranged into five (5) series. Series have been designated for: I. Decision Briefs; II. Regulations; III. Legislative Files; IV. Executive Orders and Directives; and V. Policy Analyst Files. These records include agendas, decision briefs, correspondence, memorandums, legislative files, briefing books, meeting notes, subject files, reports, talking points and regulations. These records document the legislative and policy priorities of the Kaine administration (2006-2010). This collection also includes records from Governor Mark Warner's administration (2002-2006).
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR-MARK WARNER
Several of Governor Kaine's education initiatives (teacher quality and high school reform) began during the administration of Governor Mark Warner (2002-2006). Researchers should also review A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 1998-2006.
Contents List
- I. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 2002-2010., Extent: 6.0 cubic feet (6 boxes). (Box 1-6;)
  This series is housed in 6 boxes and subdivided by Higher Education and State Agencies. Additional records may be found in Series III. Correspondence, Office of the Secretary and Series VIII. Special Projects and Studies. This series contains agendas, agreements, briefing books, correspondence, handouts, memorandums, notes, presentations, and reports.
  - Higher Education
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, Single Audit Report, 2006 June 30. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dept. of Accounts, Report on Statewide Financial Management and Compliance, 2006 June 30. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Governor Mark Warner's Higher Education Budget Meeting, 2003 November 16. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Christopher Newport University (CNU), 2006. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Eastern Virginia Medical School (EVMS), 2007-2008. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - George Mason University (GMU), 2005-2008. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - James Madison University (JMU), 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Longwood University, 2006-2007. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Baldwin College, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mary Washington University, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Norfolk State University (NSU), 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Old Dominion University (ODU), 2005-2008. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Radford University, 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Richard Bland College, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - University of Virginia (UVA), 2003; 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - University of Virginia Medical Center, 2006-2008. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - University of Virginia College at Wise, 2003; 2006. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2005. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2006. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2006. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2007. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2008. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2009 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2003 May 21. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2009 July 16. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2009 September 17. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2009 November 12. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), 2006-2008. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Institute of Marine Science, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Modeling, Analysis and Simulation Center (VMASC), 2008. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Military Institute (VMI), 2006-2008. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Virginia State University (VSU), 2005-2008. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Virginia State University (VSU), 2009 September 10-11. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Tech, 2006; 2008. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - College of William and Mary, 2005-2009. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Eastern Shore Community College, 2007. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Germanna Community College, 2006; 2008. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Lord Fairfax Community College, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mountain Empire Community College, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - New River Community College, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Northern Virginia Community College, 2006; 2008. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Patrick Henry Community College, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Paul D. Camp Community College, 2007. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Piedmont Virginia Community College, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Rappahannock Community College, 2007. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Southside Virginia Community College, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Thomas Nelson Community College, 2004. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Highlands Community College, 2006. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Wytheville Community College, 2002; 2009. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2005. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2006 January-2006 March. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2006 April-2006 June. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2006 July-2006 August. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2006 September-2006 October. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2006 November-2006 December. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2007 January-2007 June. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2007 July-2007 August. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2007 September-2007 December. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 January-2008 April. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 May-2008 July. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 August. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 August 29. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 September. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 September-2008 October. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2008 November-2008 December. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2009 January-2009 February. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2009 March-2009 April. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2009 May-2009 July. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2009 August-2009 October. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2009 November-2010 January. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - State Agencies
    - Department of Accounts, 2007. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 2008-2009. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 2006-2009. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 2007-2008. (Box 3, Folder 16a)
    - Frontier Culture Museum, 2007-2008. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gunston Hall Plantation, 2008. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2005-2007. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2008 November 13-14. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2008 November 13-14. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2008-2009. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2009 May 14-15. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2009 October 28. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Library of Virginia, 2006; 2008. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Patrick Henry National Memorial, 2008-2009. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Commission for the Arts, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Commission on Youth, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Commission on Youth, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 11a)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 2006-2007. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - American Civil War Center at Historic Tredegar, 2009. (Box 4, Folder 12a)
  - State Agencies-Virginia Dept. of Education
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2006 July 26. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2006 September 27. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2006 October 25. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2006 November 29. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 January 10. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 February 28. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 March 29 (1 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 March 29 (2 of 2). (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 April 27. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 May 30-31. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 June 28. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 July 25. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 September 26 (1 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2007 September 26 (2 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 January 10. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 February 21. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 March 19. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 April 23-24. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 May 22. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 June 19. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 July 17. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 September 25 (1 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 September 25 (2 of 2). (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 October 23. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2008 November 20. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 January 15. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 February 19. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 March 26. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 April 29-30. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 May 28. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Board of Education Meeting Packet, 2009 June 25. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2005 December-2006 July. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2006 August-2007 February. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2007 March-2009 February. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- II. Constituent Correspondence, 2006-2010., Extent: 8.0 cubic feet (8 boxes). (Box 7-14)
  The Constituent Correspondence series is housed in 8 archival boxes and is arranged roughly by chronological order by last action taken. This series documents constituent correspondence received by the Office of the Secretary of Education during Governor Tim Kaine's administration. This series contains correspondence from various constituents to Governor Tim Kaine, along with a copy of Tom Morris' letter in response, and a page from the people summary database which includes the name, address, and phone number of the correspondent. Each letter in this series contains a unique tracking number assigned by the Governor's Office Constituent Services. Records are arranged by outgoing tracking number.